<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>tahsin faraz khan</title><description>cultures coexist, boundaries blur</description><link>https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/</link><item><title>Hollow Horizons</title><link>https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/hollow-horizons/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/hollow-horizons/</guid><description>An industrialist titan with Parsi Zoroastrian roots ideates an ingenious automobile affordable for his average countryman, costing ₹1,00,000, or just above $1,000. The industrialist’s vision is inherently Hegelian, for the assembly of his automobile, essentially an elevator of socioeconomic standards for his people, necessitates degenerating nature.</description><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 1984 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;“After you have exhausted what there is in business, politics, conviviality, love, and so on — have found that none of these finally satisfy, or permanently wear — what remains? Nature remains,” reads The Marginalian’s tweet, quoting the American poet Walt Whitman. Whitman, revisiting the rousing of his rejuvenation while writing to a dear friend a decade after his paralytic ordeal reveals nature, as Popova recounts, as his pivotal private nurse — but for how long will Whitman&apos;s quote hold? Or for how long nature can retain its ontological category?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sally Rooney echoes Whitman’s reverence for nature en passant in The Irish Times, arguing it’s high time we spring to action, for the materialists stand singleminded in molesting mother nature for material gains, and the maimed mother can only bear so many more blows. It’s capitalism catalyzing nature’s desolation, Rooney maintains, citing several sources, statistics, and her own convictions, highlighting how insatiable greed, by both consumers and creators, keeps the capitalistic cog running, and that the cog will come to a halt only when there is no nature left to milk. Rooney realizes that the zeitgeist is somewhat self-aware, conscious of its careless consumption-centric conventions, but she worries if this Jungian individualization alone is enough to counter the colossal calamity caused by the sanctimonious capitalist degenerates. So the sole solution the 33-year-old screenwriter sees, sharing the Arendtian sentiment, is ardent activism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pilgrims board the return train home with a renewed sense of purpose and security induced by days of devotion in the birthplace of God. The train takes about 18 hours to reach its destination, but each passing hour is a lifetime for the pilgrims bubbling in high spirits to share their slices of experience with loved ones. Twelve lifetimes pass by, and the train takes a customary pause at a remote station. The pilgrims are living in the moment, singing, chanting, chatting, snacking, for home is on the horizon — home remains on the horizon, forever, as one thing leads to another and panic ensues as the train compartment is set ablaze by a mob, and, nowhere to run, with compartment exits blocked by the mob, the pilgrims, in the shape of men, women, and children, asphyxiate and burn to a crisp. Their renewed sense of purpose and security after days of devotion is deemed worthless as the incompetent God stands in silence. The ashes of devotees inflame the religious community, the amygdala takes over from the frontal cortex, animalistic instinct kicks in, craving for vengeance consumes the mind as the feeling of being wronged, of helplessness, sends shivers down the soul, belief in God gets suspended, and the collective consciousness cries for blood. The collective community of the opposing identity is deemed guilty, and, as human horror knows no bounds, their homes are reduced to debris, children are burnt alive, women are disfigured, raped, have their genitalia mutilated in front of their loved ones. The incompetent God, yet again, as always, stands in silence, as does the state’s nationalist leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An industrialist titan with Parsi Zoroastrian roots ideates an ingenious automobile affordable for his average countryman, costing ₹1,00,000, or just above $1,000. The industrialist’s vision is inherently Hegelian, for the assembly of his automobile, essentially an elevator of socioeconomic standards for his people, necessitates degenerating nature. A rural fertile farmland is found fitting to actualize the industrialist’s idea. The pragmatic Marxist state government is informed of the industrialist’s vision, and, quick as a wink, sensing the $15 billion project as a strong source of a domino effect for trade and employment imperative to the impoverished area’s growth, plays the colonial card called the Land Acquisition Act, and seizes ~4 km² of land from the natives, claiming “public purpose.” Some find solace in the offered compensation corresponding to the land value, while others, having lost their livelihood, are antagonized at the government twerking for the industrialist. Soon enough, the situation escalates, essentially extending an invitation to politicians. Some politicians side with the industrialist, sensing the potential socioeconomic upgrade for the place, while others, recognizing the offered compensation’s inadequacy on top of its exclusivity, share the natives’ infuriation. Empowered by the state government, the industrialist starts setting up the automobile factory. Sstanchioned by a progressive pragmatist party, the natives take to the streets to protest. Chaos ensues, indefinite sit-in in front of the factory gate is organized, blood is shed, lives are lost, the movement gains national and international recognition, and finally, after 30 long months, the pragmatic Marxist state government yields and the industrialist turns tail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nationalist leader monitoring the drama from the opposite end of the country slides into the industrialist’s DMs with promises of a surrounding attuned to stimulate him. Wooed, the industrialist swipes right and decides to take the relationship forward. Soon enough, their chemistry has a domino effect. The industrialist succeeds in bringing his vision to life, manifesting multitudes of direct and indirect jobs in related and non-related sectors, leading to a surge in socioeconomic standards, and eventually a positive public image of the nationalist leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had the pragmatic Marxist state government handled the situation better, had the progressive pragmatist opposition been a better negotiator, their state would’ve enjoyed the socioeconomic upgrade. But incompetence on their part let loose the golden goose, and the marginalized and vulnerable still pay the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erik ten Hag’s takeover as the Manchester United manager reignites optimism within the team and broader club community alike. The man with a terrific track record owing to his intricate tactical system is now expected to revitalize the Theater of Dreams. Ten Hag tries to replicate his tactical system even when the players at his disposal are neither attuned nor befit the system, and ultimately, obviously, his pursuit falls flat. The club hierarchy finally comes to senses two years later, finding the team back on square one, and the manager is shown the exit. Ten Hag is a case of naive, anti-Hegelian, anti-Platonian idealism, an idealism where ideals take the driving seat rather than pragmatism — and such an approach ends up hurting the most vulnerable more often than not while creating new problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Is there even a point to strive towards a higher ideal? A more perfect democracy?” ponders The Beat Philosopher. Is there? Who knows? Certainly not the insincere idealists, optimists, capitalists, or activists.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>Articles</category><author>tahsin faraz khan</author></item><item><title>Luck and Other Notions</title><link>https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/luck-and-other-notions/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/luck-and-other-notions/</guid><description>“Everything is a placebo effect, Adya. And if you know that, you can use it to your advantage.” “Isn’t that wrong?” “Wrong?” “As in, immoral?” “It’s good if you use it for good, bad if you use it for bad. It’s not necessarily a good or a bad thing in itself.”</description><pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 1971 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;“I like you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You guys should visit Mumbai next time. You’ll come, won’t you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Y—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The next time you plan a travel, plan it for my place?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Mumbai City will play Al Hilal soon, so maybe I can come watch the match live.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Great.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hello? Where the fuck are you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, hello. I’ll be there in about 20 minutes.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Still 20 minutes? You sound like a broken record. How far exactly did you wander off, man?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m walking as fast as I can, bro. We went much further than planned, all the way to the remotest village here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, I’m with the girl.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The girl?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The girl from the reception, remember?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, yeah, of course you are. She’s going to be joining us?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah. Weirdly enough, she seems interested in us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Us?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, I told her about you, Zayn.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Interesting. Well, hurry up. I’ve aged waiting for you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Who’s that girl talking to the receptionist?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We entered the hostel together, and we’re both tourists here, so I don’t have any more information than you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s called small talk, maybe try to learn it. By the way, she’s cute, isn’t she?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Maybe you should go talk to her.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You know what? I will.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Cool, good luck. Meanwhile, I’ll go find our room and freshen up, and rest a while.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re not going hiking with me? It seems the girl is also asking about hiking routes. Maybe she’ll join us?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We walked five kilometers from the bus stop to the hostel on hills and valleys — that’s hiking enough for me for one day. See you in the evening.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So, you’re Zayn? Your friend here told me a lot about you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He did? Haha, that’s nice. What all did he blabber away?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, he mentioned that you’re also a freelancer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re a freelancer too? That’s wonderful, it’s rare for me to find folks like us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, yeah. So what do you do?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m in marketing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Isn’t that nice? I’m trying to get into marketing as well, you know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are you? Interesting.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah. I mean, I have a marketing-adjacent gig right now, but I want to transition completely into the field at some point.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I see.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So, is this your first time visiting Kasol?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not really, I’ve visited this place — if I remember correctly — twice before.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, you like it here?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I like the mountains, they speak to me — they’re calm, majestic, and there’s an air of coolness around them, both literally and metaphorically.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Interesting. This is my first time visiting Kasol — well, north India in general — and I’m already loving it here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s nice. You travel a lot?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’ve been traveling frequently recently, yeah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ah, I see. You know what? I’m starving. How about we order something?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sounds great, I’m hungry as well. What should we order?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hmm…let’s look at the menu. I think I’ll order this Deluxe Forest Pizza and a White Sauce Pasta. How about you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well…I think I’ll order the cheese noodles, the Mushroom fries, and some drinks — how about we share everything?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s actually a great idea. Cho, why don’t you also order something, and we’ll share.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ah, you’re finally here. Cho told me you were working. Can’t keep your hands off work even during a trip?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha. Well, that’s just life for a freelancer. You’d know, wouldn’t you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, yeah. And that’s why I’ve stopped packing my laptop. You shouldn’t either next time, you know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Smart girl, Adya.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ha. Uh, it’s getting cold, isn’t it? I didn’t expect the weather to change this much. I didn’t even pack any winter wear.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The temperature drops here with the day— I have an extra jacket in my room, do you want me to bring it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nah, that’s fine, I can put on a shirt on top of this. Besides, the whisky and weed will warm me up.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are you sure?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, it’s okay.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hmm…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s lovely, isn’t it? Chilling with old and new friends, drinking and dining in this warmly lit, low-murmuring café overlooking the scenic hills while the band performs in the background. I’m loving the experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It is lovely. Can I try the joint?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh sure, haha. Here— ”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So, what hobbies do you have?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love reading, watching stuff.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I love watching stuff too. What are your favorite shows?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hmm…let’s see. The shows I’ve watched the most are The Big Bang Theory, Modern Family—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oooh I love Modern Family.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Really? Well, same pinch.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, who’s your favorite character?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Jay and Manny.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m surprised you didn’t say Gloria.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hahahaha, I like her too. Who doesn’t, I mean?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hahaha, yeah. You watch Bollywood much?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not really, the last Bollywood film I watched was— I’m not sure, I don’t remember. But I do remember I watched it like six months ago with a friend I visited in Delhi. I was staying in his flat, and he made me watch it. You’ve been to Delhi?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I haven’t. I mean, I’ve visited Delhi as a station during my travels, so technically, yeah. But I haven’t stayed long enough to explore the place, if that’s what you’re asking. You like it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t like it. Delhi has its advantages in terms of its proximity to places worth traveling to and the food, but there are better places to live I guess.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Is it so— hey, these cheese balls are delicious. Why don’t you try these?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure— Umm, God, you’re so right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I know, I always am. Just out of curiosity, do you believe in God?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Not really. Why?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“So you’re an atheist?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, I don’t like to assign labels, but okay.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Interesting. What do you say during formal procedures or write while filling forms?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Muslim, or Hindu, or whatever suits the specific scenario best.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, you know, sometimes I — wait, I’m starting to feel unwell. I think it’s all the booze and smoke.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Do you want to rest?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Probably. You don’t seem tipsy or high?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, the drugs don’t affect me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Is that so? Why is that?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It appears so. Well—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“God, my headache’s getting worse. I’m sorry, I think I’m done for the night.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh yeah, of course. I hope you feel better by the morning. Bye, Adya. Take care.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Bye, Zayn — Alia, could you please escort me to our room? Thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You’re back soon. Nice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And you’re still here. Nice”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha. How are you feeling now?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s nice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s getting chillier, isn’t it? Do you want to go indoors, to the arcade maybe? We can play pool or something.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sounds good. Let’s get inside and — wait, let me get a cup of tea real quick, the café’s about to close. Do you want something?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure, I—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You like coffee, isn’t it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Adya, do you want me to help you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure, I could use some help.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay. So, give me your hand, let me help you get down.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here–”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now, place your foot on the rock on the right. Careful.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay, now step down slowly– wait, hand me your backpack first.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here–”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now step down, easy. Put all your weight on my palm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Done.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Great, now let’s just follow Cho’s lead. We’ll reach the stream in no time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Cho, slow down, man. How long until we reach the stream?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Less than 15 minutes. Pass me your water bottle, will you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Here–”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Did you bring something to eat? I thought we could sit in the Parvati Valley for like half an hour before leaving for Chalal. Is that okay?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yes and yes. Let&apos;s sit on the rocks, throw stones in the stream, and make some wishes as we listen to the therapeutic sound of water crashing into the stones and savor cookies and chips and tea – or coffee. Adya, what do you say?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That sounds nice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And— okay, now be careful from here, folks. The rocks are slippery, and the water flow doesn’t help. Cho, why don’t you get in front and lead us?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean why? Adya’s new to the place.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I know, but why the hell should I lead? Why can’t you lead?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Because you’ve explored this place more than me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“That’s not true, this is also my third trip to Kasol.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nope, you got here once without me during our college days, remember?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, but a difference of one isn’t much.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s enough to give you an upper hand, and subsequently, to settle this debate. Oh, and you also went hiking the other day.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why do I feel like you’re using me as a lab rat?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, that&apos;s easy. Because you&apos;re a cynic.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Or maybe you want me to lead because if I slip or fall over and something happens to me, you can avoid the same situation?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Now that you mention it, I’d love for that to happen.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Or is it that maybe you want to spe–”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just take the lead, man. Please?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Relax, bro. I’m just messing with you. Follow the king, you sheeps.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The plural of sheep is sheep, not sheeps. A worthy king would know– okay okay okay, I’m sorry, please don’t come back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Are you sure he’s a Sikh Guru?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think so, yeah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Any fresh ideas?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Honestly– wait, take your phone out.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why– Oh, Lens?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yeah.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Nice, let me just scan this quickly…..whaaat?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What? Show me.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Look, it just shows random Sikh people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hmm..that’s racist, Google.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Haha, forget it. Let’s just ask the receptionist, I’m assuming he’d know.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Good idea. Let’s go down.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, you were right, he’s indeed a Sikh Guru. Guru Angad, to be precise, the second one.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hah, that’s our mystery solved.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yep. Give me a high five.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“High five.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By the way, do you really think is a criminal meeting place?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hahaha. Nah, I was just messing with Cho.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Really?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Everything is a placebo effect, Adya. And if you know that, you can use it to your advantage.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Isn’t that wrong?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wrong?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“As in, immoral?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“It’s good if you use it for good, bad if you use it for bad. It’s not necessarily a good or a bad thing in itself.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, let’s not keep Cho waiting any longer.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The hell is this place, bro?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Looks like a cafe-disco hybrid that also serves as a meeting point for the leaders of organized crime in this city and simultaneously a front for money laundering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hahaha”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right? I mean, why is the disco blocked by armed guards in a place full of hippies? And why does a disco so tiny require a whole separate floor? And why is the restaurant nearer to the disco, not this cafe? I mean, why waste so much space? The property rent or cost here isn’t exactly low here. They must be losing money with this setup — unless—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hahahaha, stop it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No, you stop laughing, Adya. How is that funny? If anything, Zayn is being paranoid, all the drinking and smoking from last night has turned his brain into mush. Could it not just be that they know the tourists very well? I mean, they’re hippies. And this spacious, open-roof cafe on the top floor makes the perfect setting for them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“If they knew the hippies well, the restaurant would be adjacent to this cafe so they wouldn’t have to walk down a flight of stairs to order food.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“You order the food first, and then come up to the cafe, Einstein.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“What if Einstien needed to order more food? Or a drink? Or anything else? When was the last time you made all your orders in one go or didn’t need anything extra?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Fine. But what does it have to do anything with this being a meeting point for criminals? Or a front for money laundering?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;”You don’t want to add friction for your customers, especially when your target audience is lazy hippies — unless you don’t really care about it, and you’re making most of your profits in another way. Besides, did you notice how the guards below have a clear, unblocked view of the entire cafe as well as the entrance to the building– don’t turn around, man.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Okay?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“And do you notice how it appears to be a disco, with the flickering lights and all, but did you hear people dancing inside?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know, I’m not sure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Guys, guys. I’m feeling a bit excluded here.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Oh, we’re sorry, Adya.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“WE are not sorry, you’re the only one who should be sorry. You started the whole conspiracy theory.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Well, you were the one who noticed this place seemed strange, I was just responding to you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“But you—”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“GUYS.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“...”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“...”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“By the way, do either of you know that person in the poster over there?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“No idea.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“He’s one of the ten Sikh gurus, that I know, but I can’t quite recall his name. Why?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Just curious.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Ah okay.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I’m going to the other side to take a closer look. Do you want to come with me, Zayn?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Sure.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Yep.”&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>Articles</category><author>tahsin faraz khan</author></item><item><title>Echoes of the Evening</title><link>https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/echoes-of-the-evening/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/echoes-of-the-evening/</guid><description>Sophie Brooks, Phil Jackson, and Emma Oakley walk onto the stage. Dr. Brooks, associate professor of sociology and communications, dressed as if to pay tribute to Malin Buska at Cannes 2017, sits on the left corner of the white Lawson while Mr. Jackson, the acclaimed writer and the only speaker who seems to have missed the evening’s fashion memo, takes the opposite corner.</description><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 1959 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;1
In a turtleneck almost as bright as her smile and a dark pleated skirt to complement it, with nail polish and lipstick in a deeper, her characteristic red shade neatly tying up the look, arms mostly crossed but moving at times to usher the guests, Louise Kelly stands loudly silent on the stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All other eyes now share my focus, and Ms. Kelly sets the evening in motion, introducing herself, the guests, and the specifics of the evening. She exits the stage, giving way to the panelists, and takes a seat somewhere behind me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event starts 15 minutes late, but it’s timely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.1
Sophie Brooks, Phil Jackson, and Emma Oakley walk onto the stage. Dr. Brooks, associate professor of sociology and communications, dressed as if to pay tribute to Malin Buska at Cannes 2017, sits on the left corner of the white Lawson while Mr. Jackson, the acclaimed writer and the only speaker who seems to have missed the evening’s fashion memo, takes the opposite corner. Dr. Oakley, a theologian by training but a writer by trade, an eclectic and versatile one at that, occupies the chair reserved for moderators. Dr. Oakley introduces the topic and her ground rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speakers, showing regard for the rules, have a quickfire exchange, and Dr. Brooks decides to go first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Brooks: Politics is inherently about vibes. [Social media] creates an environment in which we recognize vibes a bit more than we used to, but it’s not the case that we invented them suddenly in the 2020s. I think we are much less rational than we imagine ourselves to be. There’s a tendency, we think that we verify facts, there is objective deliberation, and we come to a conclusion, but no – we’re part of political tribes, we are part of identities, and what we see in media research, interestingly, proven through quantitative studies, that these tribal identities trumps other considerations. So, it’s not the case that people are not exposed to facts or contrasting opinions, they are exposed to them but filter them differently, through their preexisting ideologies and identities and tribal connections, and that I think is an inherent component of politics again, not something that we had never had beforehand. But I think it has become more salient through new tech and other changes, fact of which we can understand better if we read Phil’s book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr. Jackson: I think, well, first of all, I think why politics is so interesting is because it covers such a vast range of human behavior and conduct. I mean, it can be extremely high-minded about first principles and philosophical ideas about how society should be run in practice, and it can be as stupid as how somebody looks. And that’s just, you know, the art of it. So, I think, in the actual practice of politics, feelings affect, you know, general dislike of people for reasons that are not rational, or you have to look for reasons deeper than at face value, are always gonna be a part of it. I think rhetoric has always been a part of democratic politics to appeal to public opinion and that’s not pure reason that includes appeals to people’s emotions, but I do believe there’s technology now that makes it easier to make those sorts of appeals where it used to take a lot of labor, and its also easy to see the results, or maybe we think we see the results of those kinds of appeals to emotions, so I think we have more vibe machines? I know that sounds stupid but I think, yeah, feelings and emotionality have always been a part of political appeals.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Brooks, who has written two books on sociopolitical theory and is now working on a third, and Mr. Jackson, who has words in the country’s top publications, argue that “political vibes” are only more apparent now due to the zeitgeist’s interconnectedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the fashionable thing is insincere identity politics, where seemingly full-grown people behave like kids and attack others based on identity or false taboo labels rather than genuine well-meaning criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, the fashionable thing is to paint people in broad strokes with the brush of Communism /Marxism/Socialism. Sanders, Harris, and Gandhi are often painted as such. My problem here is not ideological orientation but nomenclature and categorization. Those people, like any other rational person, favor economic equality, personal liberty, social welfare, and also capitalism — and rightfully so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In capitalism, we get probably the most effective weapon to fight personal or national economic stagnation and bring people together, even better than religion perhaps. The better one wields that weapon, the more lives one intersects, intertwines, and influences, and the more others directly or indirectly depend, and the more powerful one becomes as a market regulator and economy influencer. And with more power, comes more responsibility, so the more accountable one should be held. That’s just a tradeoff inherent to the capitalistic structure, it seems to me — either don’t go around venturing or dare to influence and be held accountable. A market-oriented economy with enough incentives and opportunities for innovation and entrepreneurship should go hand in hand with economic regulations to protect the less privileged from inequality and exploitation. You must see to it that the less-privileged and more-privileged, given equal effort, have equal playing ground. You want every individual of yours to have enough civic and economic liberties to be able to make the best out of their opportunities for personal, social, or professional growth, and only then do we get a close-to-optimal socioeconomic framework that balances individual, national, and civilizational growth with minimal suffering for people and nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a matter of ideology, that you HAVE to care about other people or nature. It’s just that we are humans, and humanity comes first. It’s the same as gender discourse but from a different pov: much like the right sees birth-rate collapse, the left sees global warming or climate change as risks to humanity. But people from either group who go around attacking other people don’t actually understand or really care about those things. To paraphrase Thomas McKenzie talking to a Nazi Jojo in Jojo Rabbit, they just want to be a part of a club — a club that’s more interested in playing identity politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin Luther King was “woke” when he dreamt and fought for racial equality. Gandhi was “woke” when he decided enough was enough and drove the British away from India with his protests and call for reforms, resulting in an independent India. Ben Franklin was “woke” with his rallying opposition to the British monarchy under King George III and his role in the American Revolution. Muhammed was “woke” when he criticized polytheism, slavery, female infanticide, and elitism. Jesus was a “woke” Jew who criticized Herod Antipas, Caiaphas, the Pharisees, and the Sadducees. All, rather interestingly, were the far-left of their time. All of them would’ve been branded as “cultural Marxists” or “postmodern neo-Marxists” by their Jordan Peterson, with different versions of identity politics and oppressed-oppressor narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Brooks and Mr. Jackson are right in saying that we are idiots. At its broadest, there’s only one reason for idiocy: bias. Bias prevents us from using our intellect at its full capacity and intensity. Bias infiltrates our mental system through different mediums, but it propagates predominantly through the virus called religion. Traditionalism, nationalism, ethnocentrism, xenophobia, sexism, and casteism are the other major types of viruses that carry the disease of bias. Identity is one thing, being proud of yours is another, but bias against other identities is counterproductive in an increasingly smaller and more connected world, thanks to technology and capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maslow’s Hierarchy of Needs needs to have another layer at the bottom called “Identity Construction” or something because creating identities based on some difference feels inherently human to me. Evolution has shaped our brains to almost instinctively, automatically, and subconsciously form some sort of “us vs them” framework — as basic and fundamental as good vs bad, our tribe vs the other tribe, or as complex and absurd as our religion vs their religion, our sect vs theirs, or engineers vs physicists, accelerationists vs degrowthers, pronatalists vs antinatalists, etc. Despite eons of evolution, we’re still monkeys in forests.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>Articles</category><author>tahsin faraz khan</author></item><item><title>The Idea of Sally Rooney</title><link>https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/hometown/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://tahsinfarazkhan.com/posts/hometown/</guid><description>I speak of the 33-year-old writer as if I’ve known her personally for years, and I’m almost apologetic upon realization. But I want to have known her personally for years, and an amok imagination is my only recourse.</description><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 1921 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The sound of Sally Rooney’s supersonic exploits has been echoing near my ears since she burst onto the stage with Conversations With Friends, but I never really bothered to give her any attention. I’ve been more or less familiar with her body of work, its nature and style — I knew of millennials’ soft spot for her and of critics being kind to her, I knew she writes as if she were the love child of Colleen Hoover and Virginia Woolf, and I knew she likes to travel the perennial paths in a Tesla — although, again, I’m yet to read a Rooney novel. Quite frankly, I&apos;ve been indifferent to her work or even her existence, but it all changed recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rooney often visits me in third places, now that she has Intermezzo to promote. I also overhear people talking about her in those third places, and they speak of her with admiration. Many of those people are well-acquainted with classic literature, some accomplished writers themselves, so naturally, I’m inclined to trust their judgment. And when she visited me with Merve Emre recently on Twitter, I couldn’t help but entertain her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above the introduction and below the title Loving the Limitations of the Novel: A Conversation between Sally Rooney and Merve Emre, there’s an image of Rooney standing against the wall wearing a long-sleeved pullover and loose-fitting trousers, hands in her pockets, poised, her scrutinizing eyes staring right into mine. I stare back into hers for a good few seconds. I sense she has that look — the look of maturity beyond one’s age, the look of a rather eccentric intersection of nonchalance and curiosity, the look alluding to a reservoir of rich, complicated stories buried deep inside, the look of having experienced or imagined sorrow in its breadth and depth, the way Taylor Swift’s “tortured poet” would look, the look that belongs to great artists and philosophers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People in my neighborhood are intrusive, they often need a twist on the arm. Just yesterday, a man walked up my porch and to my main gate. He must’ve stood there for like five minutes — I saw on the CCTV footage — before ringing the bell. He wanted in under the pretense of presenting a sales pitch, or maybe he really did want to sell something, but I dismissed his requests and sent him away. I’m trying to be perceived as less nice. It’s not Canada, you know,” Erica tells me during one of our stand-ups. Erika has a lot on her plate. She manages her local and international departmentalized teams, finalizes decisions by interior designers and architects, and oversees regional sales and marketing. In between, she picks up her kids from school, studies to get her realtor license, spends time with her family, and sleeps — all while trying to adapt to the new climate and social dynamics of South Florida. Given the nature of our relationship, I suppress my impulse to probe her for the description of the demeanor of her desire. Borrowing all the pixels of her psyche she lets me through our interactions and piecing them all through imagination, however, I do visualize it. I see that Erica’s demeanor of desire is one that betrays her nature, an armor she wants to wear to avert predators or the pernicious gaze. I understand where she’s coming from, but I don’t want to. I want to tell her ballerina that dancing is difficult with the armor on, and it comes at the cost of weighing yourself down. I want to tell her she might not be able to take the armor off at some point for she would become one with it, losing her exuberance and animated expressions forever. “If I were you, I wouldn’t change, because why change for people you don’t like? If you’re nice, people think, people assume you’re naive. But who cares what some schmuck thinks when you know yourself,” I reply. Erika stares at me, her lips play along but her eyes betray her in concealing a half-smile. She asks me about the progress of our project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Why don’t you take it off? You must be burning up in this heat,” my mother asks Nargis. She appears to nod but her head changes course midair, moving sideways rather than upwards. She continues scrubbing the floor of our house, wrapped in sweat of labor, and her niqab. Nargis first put on the niqab when she was 7, upon being made aware of her growing body and that not covering herself up from head to toe speaks of her character. Since then, she has never left the house with her character open to interpretation — to the men in her neighborhood or her God. Now 37, she is a domestic help at my home and a few others in my community, earning just about enough to hold onto her world desperately as it seeps and droops and shows signs of falling apart. Her dainty hands bear scars from her jobless, drunkard husband instead of the colorful bangles they deserve, her face with wrinkles and dark circles of toil that send her four kids to school lie about her real age, but she doesn’t care. Nargis wants to keep her niqab on, not wanting to invite any more trouble, but perhaps she also wants to live in a world where she needn’t wear it to avoid judgment from men or her God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rooney has the demeanor Erika desires, that Nargis’ niqab actualizes by proxy. It’s not a persona programmed in haste for a desired output, unlike Erika’s desire or Nargis’ niqab, but a property intrinsic to her personality — a property slowly and organically absorbed into her identity as she built a nuanced awareness of the world and the complexities of the lives in it, its rules, its systems, the strengths of that system and the holes in them. Rooney’s demeanor is a by-product of her education, awareness, and critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I speak of the 33-year-old writer as if I’ve known her personally for years, and I’m almost apologetic upon realization. But I want to have known her personally for years, and an amok imagination is my only recourse. Wait — what if my imagination is deceitful? What if it assigned her those qualities and an origin story it admires? What if her facade is also carefully contrived? What if it’s a manifestation also born out of necessity? Oh God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s what good marketing is. Good marketing is tempting, overpowering, it draws the target audience in because “this is a very complicated and noisy world. We’re not going to get a chance to get people to remember much about us. So we have to be really clear on what we want them to know about us,” as Steve Jobs said. Good marketing &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; makes the book/author more valuable in the eyes of the reader, as visakan veerasamy says. Rooney’s deep impression, a product of reviews from people I trust, her interview, and my imagination, is inviting. I never wanted to read her before, but she talks to me now, and I listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rooney talks about how she approaches writing novels, how the form evolved over time and why it did the way it did, she talks about why she writes novels, how sometimes “it’s October for her characters, but actually May,” and, among other things, the books that influenced her. Even if you don’t like Rooney or writing, if you’re even vaguely interested in psychology or philosophy, I suggest you read the interview published in The Paris Review.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>Articles</category><author>tahsin faraz khan</author></item></channel></rss>